<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An alarum to the parish, called, Olives Southwark for to awaken them out of the state of carnal security: and that they hearken to God's witness, which alwayes calls to that which is good, and doth, and ever will, stand a witness against that which is evil.</title>
            <author>Tompkins, Anthony, d. 1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62879</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828751</idno>
  <idno type="VID">33182</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240856285</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1828</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217050</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828751</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99828751e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62879)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33182)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1859:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An alarum to the parish, called, Olives Southwark for to awaken them out of the state of carnal security: and that they hearken to God's witness, which alwayes calls to that which is good, and doth, and ever will, stand a witness against that which is evil.</title>
                  <author>Tompkins, Anthony, d. 1699.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1671]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed and dated: "Written the 30th of the 1st Moneth, 1671. Anthony Tompkins.".</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Salvation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33182:1"/>
            <head>An ALARUM To the PARISH, called, Olives Southwark, For to Awaken them out of the State of CARNAL SECURITY: And that they hearken to God's Witness, Which alwayes calls to that which is Good, and doth, and ever will, stand a WITNESS against that which is Evil.</head>
            <p>WHen I have consider'd the State and Condition of you, it hath caused Sorrow in my Heart to see how you are led along from Week to Week, and from Moneth to Moneth, and from Year to Year, by such who cause you to err.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:33182:2"/>
            <p> And the End of my writing is, that ye might be awaken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of the drowsie State and Condition you are now in.</p>
            <p>If any should be hereby awakened, and enquire and ask, <hi>What shall we do, that we may come to a better State and Condition?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why this I have to say to such, Cease from Man, whose Breath is in his Nostrils; for, if you consider aright whereof he is to be accounted of, what are you the better for hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him Preach from Year to Year, that feeds you Ears with words, which does not avail you any thing? I do not deny, but you may hear good words; ye may hear the Scripture read, the which, such as Preach to you make a Trade on them; the which you know, as well as I: and some keep Journey-men, or a Journey-man, to feed your Ears with words, to the end, that you may enrich the Master of such Journey-man or men.</p>
            <p>Neighbours, I dare not flatter, but deal plainly with you; for the Lord hath caused his Light to shine out of Darkness, and hath shined into my Heart, and hath there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by discovered to me the Evil that was there inhabited, which was of the Devil, the Prince of Darkness; and now I can say, to the Honour of God, I, who was sometime in Darkness, am come to be made Light in the Lord; who is over all, God blessed forever, <hi>Amen,</hi> saith my Soul.</p>
            <p>I Having obtain'd Mercy, who was in the sight of the new and living Way, which is Christ Jesus, the Light which lighteth every man which cometh into the Word; yet lost it again in a great measure: Yet such was the Love of God unto my immortal Soul, that he did not leave striving with me; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I was in a great measure departed from the Living Way, and was gone into the way of Evil-doers, and so took pleasure in Unrighteousness; yet such was the Love of God, that he did not leave me, no<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> forsake me; such was the Love
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:33182:2"/>of the Lord to my soul, who is no Respecto<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Persons, but whosoever feareth him, and worketh Righteousness, is accepted of him.</p>
            <p>But this is my Testimony for God's Truth, which he hath vouchsafed, in his Love and Mercy, to make me a Partaker of, None can work Righteousness, but such as come to that Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Principle, which God hath plac'd in the Conscience of Man; the which is Divine, its Pure, it bears Witness against whatsoever is Evil: These things I do not write barely by hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>say, but by good Experience (so I have cause to term it) For it did judge and condemn me Evening, and Night, and Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, for evil Deeds and Words, whil'st I was in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance thereof. And to this Witness I direct you all, in the Love of God only, and for no Self-ends, nor yet to be seen in Print the Lord knows my heart; therefore let not this be slight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; for, it ought more to be look't after, and enquir'd into, then heretofore it hath been by you: Do not think 'tis enough to go to hear a man speak a few words to you, whil'st a Glass is a run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, it may be, about an Hour; for if you do, you will find one day that you were mistaken, but then it will be too late for you; if that were enough, then it were an Easie Way to Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Rest: But those that come to Happiness, must come to the Way, which the Lord hath prepar'd before the Eyes of all Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to enlighten them, and to be their Salvation.</p>
            <p>If any should enquire, <hi>What is that Light, that did lighten the</hi> Gentiles?</p>
            <p>Why, it was Christ, the Covenant of Light, which God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised, in his Love, to save thousands that were in Darkness.</p>
            <p>But some may say, <hi>We have that which they had not, therefore we need not question, but it will go well with us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this I affirm; Although ye may hear men Preach against that which they and you live in the practice of, yet if ye come not to the Light, which-did enlighten the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> you will be in Darkness; <hi>For, whatsoever maketh manifest, is Light,</hi> as it was written by an experienc'd man: <hi>Thy Commandment is a L<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mp, thy Law is Light, and the Reproof of Instruction is the Way of Life;</hi> so every one mind that which reproveth for Evil; and that, if
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33182:3"/>joyn'd to and obey'd, will be as a Light to thy Goings: For if thee or I should follow after men, and learn of them, what will they teach us, but to be Covetous and Proud of Parts and Wisdom, which wisdom is but Foolishness with God? For, the Lord is now arisen and arising, to stain the Pride of all Flesh; there shall be a Desolation upon those that have been set about a Work, which the Lord did not set to work</p>
            <p>But some may say, <hi>Who can say the Lord did not set our Ministers at work?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why this observe, and do not deal treacherously with thy own Reason, Do'st thou think that God ever imploy'd a man to do any thing for him, and did not give him strength to perform it? Do not think him to be, as he was reported to be, That ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd where he did not strow; no, no, he is not such a one: If the Lord had imploy'd these men, then it would have been done; but these have done, as others before them did; that is, Go, when as the Lord never sent them, and so did not profit the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple at all.</p>
            <p>And further, It doth appear to every unbyast mind, that these are not God's Ministers; for they look more after the Fleeces, then the Sheep: For the good Shepherd layeth down his Life for his Sheep; but the Hireling Flees, and yet looketh for the Fleeces. Call to mind what was done the year that the Lord sent the Plague amongst us; was not there more need of his work then, then before or since, if it would have done any good: But this I can say, Such are Physitians of no value, therefore cease from them; for if you do not, the Lord God of Heaven and Earth will render Vengeance upon you; therefore I warn you, who are the Inhabitants of this Parish, wherein I have a Beeing, Cease from Hirelings, both Master and Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyman, receive not any more of his Glass; but come to the Physitian of Soul and Body, he that is that good <hi>Samaritan,</hi> that bound up that which the Fine-finger'd Priest could not touch; but if that Priest was like these of our times, that make a Trade of Preaching for Money; I say, if he was like these, then he would have alighted off a Horse, or have come out of a Coach to a took up a Bag of Money; for that they love, and that is the Root of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33182:3"/>evil; if they did not, they would not covet two Parishes to gain their Money from them.</p>
            <p>But some may say, <hi>He is a Sickly Man, and therefore he doth it.</hi> (thus perhaps will some plead) But if any should plead for that which is evil, there is one, that we shall all appear before, that will be too hard for such, when no Priest shall dare to appear to take their parts; therefore partake not of their Sins, for if you do, you will be at a loss one day; were there no Receivers, there would be no Thieves: Therefore, in the Fear of God, and according to his Requirings, be ve warned, follow not the fallible; but every one turn your minds inward, to that which reproves for evil Deeds and Words; and, if heeded, it will shew where the heart is; if the mind be carnal, then is Death and Darkness over; but if the Mind and the Affections be set on things above, that are Heavenly, the Darkness will vanish away, the Son of Righteousness will be discover'd; and then you will not dare to lend an Ear to a Hireling, that Preacheth for Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; but will lend an Ear to the true Shepherd's Voyce: And this I testifie, if any incline to hear, they shall not be Hearkners in vain, if they obey that Voyce that reproves for Evil, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be on the Right-hand or on the left, if going into that which is evil, whether it be to hear such as are often confessing, and yet forsake not that which separateth from God, the which is Sin, but plead for it term of Life; and so are pleading for that which with-holdeth good things from them, and are following Teachers that preserve not their Knowledge, neither can they: <hi>For no man knoweth the things of God, but by the Spirit of God; for they are spiritually discern'd:</hi> Hear's ground sufficient (one would think) for all to sink down, and to stoop low; turn the mind inward, commune with thy own heart, and be still; and that's the best Counsel I can give: For, till I came there, I was as a wilde Heifer unaccustom'd to the Yoak; but when I came to a consideration how the case stood with me, between the God of Heaven and my own soul, I found that I had resisted his Will, and had slighted his Witness, and had cast his holy Law behind my back; and had once got a habit of Company-keeping, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Taverns and Ale-house; and could scarce buy or sell,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33182:4"/>but away to these places, although near home; and when their Marks many can bear, witness what Fruits are brought forth in such places: And whil'st I was in the practice of such things; I was not reprov'd by the Priest at all, although I did pay him six Shillings a Year. I pray what Drunkard, or Debauch't Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, hath been Excommunicated out of your Congregation, if he will but pay the Priest? And I pray, let me know one man, that was a Sinner, that is converted to be a Saint by hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Preacher? It is impossible it should be done; for it was said thus, <hi>Do'st thou say, a man should not Steal, and do'st thou Steal?</hi> To what purpose is it, if I should see a <hi>Mote</hi> in my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Eye, if I have a <hi>Beam</hi> in my own Eye? If I should under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to cast out a <hi>Mote,</hi> and have a <hi>Beam,</hi> I should be but an Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite; insomuch that, if a Covetous man should say to me, <hi>Covetousness is Sin;</hi> and should tell me, <hi>The Wages thereof is Death;</hi> I might say to such a man, <hi>Thou art the Man; and if it be well with thee, it cannot be much amiss with me.</hi> And so, here the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple take liberty by the Priest, and go hand in hand into Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and sport away their pretious time in Vanity; and when such come to Sickness, then if the Aggony of the Distemper taketh not away the Senses, then such cry out many times, <hi>Oh! what will become of my Soul? I have been so, and so;</hi> then, <hi>Oh that I might live longer, that I might have Space for to Repent:</hi> But thou should'st have read in this Book of Conscience sooner: Can'st thou read now, and could'st not see to read before? What hath open'd thy Eyes now? Was not a Measure of this in thee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now? Was not the <hi>Quaker</hi>'s Light made known to thee till now? <hi>Yes,</hi> perhaps such a one may say, <hi>it was within me, and did condemn me for what I did, that was evil; but our Teacher signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That was the light of a natural Conscience; and also said, That the</hi> Quakers <hi>were Deceivers, they being deceiv'd themselves:</hi> And also might say, <hi>It was said, That in the last dayes Antichrist shall come;</hi> and some have dar'd to say, <hi>The</hi> Quakers <hi>are them.</hi> So here these Merchants of <hi>Babylon</hi> Sell Souls, and Gain Money from Parishes for Poyson-stuff; and so poor Souls are betray'd: For, had not such a one fallen into the hands of such a Priest, he might have come to have read in the Book sooner: So that these neither
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33182:4"/>enter themselves, nor suffer others to enter, that otherwise might enter: Therefore, before it be too late, come to the Manifesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is given every one to profit withal; and that is that which will be a Guide out of that which maketh Mankind Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable. For, in this the Day of God's Power, that hath over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shaddow'd Thousands in this our day, we see it to be our Duty, to bear a faithful Testimony for him; although for the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance thereof they hazard themselves, as did he who said, <hi>Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Me;</hi> he who went before us, who lov'd not his Life to the Death, even the Death of the Cross: And this I say in the Fear of the Lord, If I could have been perswaded in my mind, that the Lord would have excus'd me, if I had neglected this Testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, which was in my Mind at times several Weeks together, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I did put my Pen to Paper concerning this. I should not have written, but lest, or for fear I should offend, I durst do no less then I have done; although for the same I may be expos'd to the censure of some, who are intail'd to their Priest for an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Livelihood; yet I shall be the more clear in the sight of him who will render to every man according to his Deeds; for God is just, and that which men sow, that shall they reap; and if so, what will become of those carnal men, that sow to the Flesh? what may such expect, but everlasting Torment? And the Lord will be just, who hath invited many by his Spirit, by the Spirit of his Son; he delighteth not in the death of Sinners, but delighteth in their returning from Sin; not in a bare Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing, but in forsaking of Sin: The Lord hath not delight in the Noise that's made by you, when ye take his Name into your mouthes, and hate to be reform'd; but yet cry, <hi>Lord have Mercy upon us,</hi> and, <hi>Christ have Mercy upon us;</hi> you call in vain, so long as ye run into sin, as a Horse rusheth into the Battel; and drink in sin, as an Ox drinketh in Water.</p>
            <p>Oh! I have often been griev'd and vex'd, to hear Children take the Lord's Name in vain, and the consideration hath been their Parents they learnt it of, who profess themselves to be <hi>Christians</hi> in words, but their deeds do manifest them to be Anti, against Christ and his People: So the desire of my soul is, that all may be awaken'd; for the Lord calls to you by an Instrument, that many Ears will shut themselves against;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33182:5"/>their Ears will not love to hear any but the Learned; but if that ever the Clouds come to be scatter'd, which the godd of the World hath cast before their Eyes; they will come to See, to Read, and to Understand, that not many Wise, not many Learned; for God hath chosen the Poor and Weak things, to confound that which is Mighty; and things that <hi>are not,</hi> to become things that <hi>are.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Christ Jesus, the Light of the World, the Captain of our Salvation, who was made perfect through Sufferings; he did not go to the great Men of the Earth, for to make their Sons Disciples, the which signifies <hi>Schollers;</hi> but took old <hi>Zebedee</hi>'s Sons, the poor <hi>Fisher</hi>-man, and the other much like unto them.</p>
            <p>The Chief-Priests and Elders lik'd pretty well what <hi>Pilate</hi> did, in setting the Learned Sentence above Christ's Head; so the spirit that now ruleth, liketh well of a <hi>Greek</hi> Scholler, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise they would not give him so much as they do, to chatter over a Speech, that effecteth no more then its seen it doth: But the <hi>false Prophets</hi> formerly did Preach Peace to the People, whil'st they put into their Mouthes; but if they refus'd; then War was prepar'd against such: But give them Money, and they will Sleep quietly by you: Be as wicked as you will, it never troubles the Priest; but if you do not give him Money, then to the <hi>Exchequer</hi> with such a one.</p>
            <p>Oh be Awaken'd! I warn all to forbear to trade with this Merchant; for if you do, you will suffer loss one day: This have I written in love to your Immortal Souls, and not in Envy to your Teacher: as he is a Man, I love him; but as he is an Enemy to the Lord and his People, I have no Unity with him: But although he be so, and there's little hopes of the <hi>Ethiopian</hi>'s changing his Skin, or the <hi>Leopard</hi> his Spots; yet I have Love, and not Enmity towards him, as he is a Man; but as he is a Flatterer, I have no unity with him; or as he is a Teacher, to do that which is evil in Conversation, although his words seem smooth, yet he will be but as a Thorn Hedge, or as rough as a Bryar; he will be for the same end, if that he doth not speedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Repent.</p>
            <p>Let this Teacher consider, how doth his Light shine: How many poor outwardly there be, Widdows and Fatherless in this
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33182:5"/>Parish? What an Example he is: Do but call to mind the Tomb that was repair'd but a few years ago: Is this man fit to be a Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher? If ye learn of him, ye may be worse, then ye are, for ought that I know: Not that I flatter any in Error; but my desire is, that those that are in the Sheep's Clothing may be discover'd, who are in their Hearts Woolfish; perhaps some may see it now, that never did see it; that's my End in writing, that the Wolves may be discover'd from the Lambs: Ye know the Lamb is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Creature; but the Woolf will rend and tear the Lambs. See who are the Fomentors of Persecution; some were Eye-Witnesses, in <hi>Grace-Church</hi>-Street, how the Priests did call to the Souldiers in an Outragious manner, <hi>Take that Man,</hi> and <hi>Take that Man:</hi> Was not <hi>Judas</hi> the Informer for the Souldiers, when he betray'd the Innocent? He did not joyn with the Lamb, but with those that crucified the Lord of Life: And so now, that spirit being in the Informers, that was in <hi>Judas</hi> for the Silver, will be Betrayers of the Seed that he hath rais'd up to bear his Heavenly Image, which hath bin marred since Prophaneness hath abounded: The man that can deck his Head with a Perriwig, is counted a man fit to have his Liberty, and wear Ribbons like a Player; but if a man does adorn his Body with such Adorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as becometh the Gospel of Christ; away with such a one, he's a <hi>Quaker:</hi> But it is better to Quake now, then hereafter; the Name was given us in Scorn, but those are Happy who are come to know thereby the Earth remov'd out of its Place; for till then, the Earth is in men's Hearts; But when the Lord comes to shake terribly the Earth, it falleth to its place, that is, under foot; such come to witness the new Creation, created a new in Christ Jesus, zealous of Good-works; such come to say, <hi>What shall I do, that I might work the works of God?</hi> Such have bid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due to Pleasures; such are come to use the World, as though they us'd it not; such are not taking thought so much, what to eat, or what to drink, how to eat, and how to drink (and not hinder the prosperity of Truth) that so they may come to bear Fruit un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God; for it is good Fruit that God accepts; then let every one examine, search, and see, what Fruit they bear; for the Ax is laid to the Root; now let all the Fruitless Trees look to it; for, the Tree that bears bad Fruit is for the Fire.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:33182:6"/>
            <p> Therefore Awake, arise, stand up to that which judgeth thee in secret for that which is evil; that's Christ, the Just Judge of all, by whom Perfection is attain'd to: For when the Judge cometh to sit upon his Throne, then which way shall the Wicked stand? There will be no room for the Enemy to act his part, but is contented then to go to those that wallow in the Filth of the Flesh, and are in the unclean nature: But Thanks be to the Lord, many are come to see the Living, and by him are made Alive, and now live to him, and not to themselves, but unto him that hath quicken'd them.</p>
            <p>So be warn'd and entreated for to mind that which judgeth and condemneth for Sin (although acted ever so secretly) and that will not only condemn for Evil, but will justifie the Well-doer, if it be believ'd in and lov'd. <hi>David</hi> said, <hi>Oh! how I love thy Judgments O Lord?</hi> Zion <hi>is Redeem'd through Judgments, and her Converts in Righteousness.</hi> So as every one cometh to be obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to that which manifests Sin in its first appearance, and will be obedient to that which is able to save the Soul, which is of more vallue then the whole World: For, what will it avail a man, <hi>to gain the whole World, and lose his own Soul?</hi> That's that which is pretious in the Sight of God; and those that are led by his Spirit, are jealous oven the Souls of all, and would not have any perish; but come to him, who is listed up as an Ensign to the Nations, that whosoever believeth in him, should be cured of the Mallady of Sin. He said, <hi>I am the Light of the World; he that will follow Me, shall not abide in Darkness, but shall have the Light of Life:</hi> Then let all follow this Comforter, who hath eas'd many a weary Soul; Rest they have found in him: He is the Lord of Sabboth; in Him is Rest: All in Him are Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated; all have been in the Degeneration: So the Lord hath prepar'd a Way for men to be Regenerated; Praises be to Him forever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Written to all that have taken up a False Rest, to awaken such.</dateline>
               <signed>A. T.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:33182:6"/>
            <head>Some Observations.</head>
            <p>VVHil'st men live in Pleasures, and in Pride, they are dead while they live.</p>
            <p>That Minister that looketh after his Gain from his Parishes more then he doth after the Souls of the People, is not Christ's but Anti, against Christ: For Christ, who is the Teacher of his People to follow him, said, <hi>Be ye Holy, for God is Holy; and be ye Perfect, as my Heavenly Father is Perfect.</hi> But what say those Belly-godds? <hi>No Perfection here.</hi> Is not this, Anti, an Opposer?</p>
            <p>Christ saith, <hi>He that loveth Father, or Mother, or Wife, or Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, or House, or Lands, more then me, is not worthy of me.</hi> Do the National Teachers do this? I appeal to the Witness of God in the Consciences of all men.</p>
            <p>Christ's Ministers were to take no thought how to Speak, or what to Answer; he said, <hi>He would be with them.</hi> But Antichrist's Ministers do take thought, they studdy.</p>
            <p>The Servants of the Lord are come to see in the <hi>Light,</hi> which shines in our hearts, to discover the <hi>Hireling</hi> by his <hi>Fruits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Minister of Jesus Christ said, <hi>Be ye Followers of us, as we are Followers of Christ Jesus.</hi> Do the National follow him? Or do they not rather go into the Way of <hi>Cain,</hi> and run greedily after the Error of <hi>Balaam,</hi> who lov'd the Wages of Unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness, and would have done Wrong to God's <hi>Israel</hi> of old, but the Lord prevented him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John</hi> saw in the Vision, <hi>An Angel flying in the mid'st of Heaven, having the Everlasting Gospel to preach.</hi> Where is Heaven, but where God dwelleth? Where is it that he dwelleth? Not with the Sorcerers, who are of the Stock of <hi>Elimas,</hi> and <hi>Simon Magus;</hi> but with those that are of an Upright Heart, who <hi>Fear and Trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at his Word:</hi> Who are <hi>Ʋpright?</hi> Who are <hi>Tremblers?</hi> Who are the <hi>Quakers? Trembling</hi> and <hi>Quaking</hi> is <hi>disdain'd; God's Dwelling-Place</hi> is <hi>villify'd;</hi> his <hi>Habitation is struck at: But its in vain for the Pot-shreds to joyn together against the Lord's Habitation.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:33182:7"/>
            <p> And such as preach the Everlasting Gospel do witness the Lord in them, and such are his Ministers; but the Covetous, the Proud, the Persecutors, the Deceivable Ones, they have one, that hath took up his Habitation in them, and by their Fruits its known who it is; for, as all good is of God, so on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, all evil is of the Devil.</p>
            <p>And farther, those that live in Covetousness are Idolaters, What, Covetous men Serve God? What, Proud men Feed God's Flock? No, No: Christ said unto <hi>Peter, Lovest thou Me more then these? —then Feed my Lambs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What, men that respect Persons? What, men that receive Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour one of another, and seek not the Honour of God only? They, or such, take upon them to bring souls to God? I bare my Testimony for God, Such err, not knowing the Scriptures nor the Power of God; but such know the Devil, the Prince of Darkness, that ruleth in those that disobey the Lord Jesus Christ.</p>
            <p>And this I can say in the truth of my Heart, If I, who am the least of many Brethren, whom the Lord hath begotten again unto a lively Hope, which is Christ in us the Hope of Glory; I say, If I might be an Instrument, for the informing of this Parish, with their Preacher also; that so they might be awaken'd out of Sleep, and that they might be rais'd from dead works, and come to serve the Living God; I should not think my Labour of Love ill-bestow'd, although for the same I may be expos'd to some Hardship, I should not matter it. And this I know, that if the Lord should make use of me farther, then yet he hath, I shall be expos'd to Sufferings; but this I can say in the Truth and in the Sincerity of my Heart, <hi>Not my will, but thy Will be done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the Lord appear'd to me Years since, he shew'd me what it would cost me, if I forsook the glory of this World, that which the World liveth in; and so I come to count the Cost: so the Lord is to be serv'd and obey'd, whatever it costeth me, be it Life or Goods, or whatever; for I know, that the evil spirit is not at all chang'd or alter'd, but will appear with what strength he hath, to obstruct and hinder; he will appear now, as well as formerly against the Godly, and whosoever
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33182:7"/>will serve the Lord, and seperate himself from the World; such are a Prey to the Wicked now, as well as formerly: For, as God is Pure and Unchangeable; so on the contrary, the Devil is Evil, and changeth not, and all those that follow the motion of his spirit, will thereby be led to Persecute; for it is so, <hi>That which is born of the Flesh will persecute that which is born of the Spirit.</hi> And the Servant of the Lord said, in dayes by past, <hi>Bonds betide me:</hi> here was one that was a Minister of Christ, but not till it pleas'd the Father to reveal his Son in him, and then he went forth to publish what the Lord had done for him and in him; he said, <hi>It had pleas'd the Father to reveal his Son</hi> In Him; <hi>and what was to be known of God was manifest</hi> In Them; so he might be a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster: He was one that preach't the same Truth, as now is held forth; which was, Christ <hi>in men, the Hope of Glory;</hi> and his Work and Labour was in the same Love, wherewith he was loved, to bring People to the Light, signifying where it was: And now is the Lord God appearing, after a long dark Night of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stacy, <hi>in</hi> and <hi>amongst</hi> a small Remnant (in comparison of the Multitude) and he will yet appear.</p>
            <p>And the Prophesie of his Servant will assuredly come to pass, that was, <hi>That the kingdoms of this World should become the Kingdoms of our Lord, and of his Christ; for his Right it is to Raign:</hi> For God, in the beginning, did not create Mankind to serve any but Himself alone; but the Enemy hath stole away the Hearts of men and women: And that old Adversary that tempted Christ, with the same, the which is, <hi>The Glory of the World;</hi> but he was the right Seed; he did not value the glory of this outward World, but resisted the Devil, and then he left him: And by the same Power many can say, to God's Glory, <hi>They have taken him for their Example, Christ Jesus, whose Kingdom was not of this World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And those that follow Him cannot Fight now, no more then they could formerly; but in obedience to Christ's Doctrine, and also Example, give the Back to the Smiter; witness the Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors at our Meeting, at <hi>Horsly-down,</hi> in the dayes lately past by; although our Persecutors said, <hi>We carry'd Weapons to do Hurt,</hi> they were Lyars, as well as formerly they were, that Crucified our
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33182:8"/>Lord and Master; him we Serve, Worship, and Obey: we meet not in Contempt of an Earthly King, but in Obedience to our Heavenly King: And the Weapons of our Warfare are not <hi>car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,</hi> but <hi>spiritual;</hi> by which Weapons sin comes to be dis-thron'd, the <hi>Sword of the Spirit,</hi> the <hi>Shield of Faith,</hi> the <hi>Helmet of Salvation,</hi> (by which we are able to quench all the fiery Darts of the Devil) these are our Weapons; and those that smite with carnal <hi>Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons,</hi> are carnal men, whether they be <hi>Professors</hi> or <hi>Prophane:</hi> For Christ Jesus did call for a Sword, and said, <hi>He that hath not a Sword, should sell his Coat, and buy him one:</hi> There was two, and that was enough to shew his Strength outwardly; for when the Priests Gang, of the baser sort, came to take him, for to put him to <hi>death,</hi> one of his Souldiers drew, and presently smote [mark] no want of Courage, although a great Multitude was there; but in Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Great King's Commands, he put up the <hi>carnal Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon;</hi> Christ said, <hi>His Kingdom was not of this World, therefore could not Fight with carnal Weapons; neither yet against Brother, nor Enemy;</hi> but <hi>if Brother offended, forgive him; if Enemy Hunger, give him Bread; if he Thirst, give him Drink; Love Enemies.</hi> And this I can say to the Honour of God, who hath created in me a New Heart, and hath renew'd his own Right Spirit in me, I shall signifie it to his Praise, That the man, or men, who did most abuse me at <hi>Horsly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>down,</hi> I could freely have communicated to him of what I have or do enjoy, whether Outwardly, or that's given me Inwardly; if by so doing, I might have been beneficial to his Immortal Soul thereby, but not to serve their sinful Lusts with. And now is that Prophesie a fulfilling, which was, <hi>That the Swords should be beaten into Plough shares, and the Spears into Pruning-hooks; Nation shall not rise against Nation, neither shall they learn War any more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Objection hath been, <hi>If all should be like you</hi> Quakers, <hi>an Enemy might cut our Throats, a forraign Nation might come in and do it.</hi> What's the cause of this Fearfulness? Is it because ye have right to the Promises, or because ye have none? But consider the Lillies of the Field; Doth not the Lord cloth the Grass? Doth not the Lord feed, or send Food for the Ravens? Doth he not take care of Sparrows? Oh Faithless Generation! But the Cause is known to many now, as well as formerly; for did People serve
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33182:8"/>the Lord, then they might expect him to be their Deliverer: But they mind Earthly things; their Bellies they offer Sacrifices un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; the Lord is very little in their minds, but Pleasure or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit they are busied about, and so they forget God: And how should such think, that the Lord should remember them?</p>
            <p>This, in the same Love to you, which the the Lord visited me, do I write; and not in any Enmity against any man, or men, as men; for I desire the good of all men, and their chiefest Good too; For, all outward things will have an End; but it is to the inward Principle that I direct you all, who have been profitted by the Tallent given unto me to profit withal; it is from him, and of him, who is God over all the Works of his own Hands, who is to be Prais'd and Magnify'd forever by me his Servant,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Anthony Tompkins.</signed>
               <date>Written the 30th of the 1st Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, 1671.</date>
            </closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>But thus saith the Lord, concerning the Prophets that make my People Err, that Bite with their Teeth, and cry, Peace; and he that putteth not into their Mouthes, they even prepare War against him,</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Micah 3.5.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>Therefore Night shall be unto you, that ye shall not have a Vision; and it shall be dark unto you, that ye shall not Divine; and the Sun shall go down over the Prophets, and the day shall be Dark over them,</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Mic. 3.6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>